Guide to the John Hays Hammond, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Hays Hammond, Jr. papers
1912-1963
MS 863
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
Printed patents, reports and related material on his system for the radio control of torpedoes, inventions for musical instruments and scrapbooks of newspaper clippings and congressional publications about Hammond and his work. Half the collection is made up of clippings.
Hammond, John Hays, 1888-1965
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the John Hays Hammond, Jr. estate, 1965.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged by type of material.
Biographical / Historical
Inventor; B.S., Sheffield Scientific School, Yale, 1910; pioneer in systems radio control of moving objects (torpedoes, ships, etc.); president Radio Engineering Co. of N.Y., Hammond Research Corp. of Mass.; inventor of improved methods of phonographic reproduction, other inventions relating to radio telephony and telegraphy, radar, pipe organ mechanisms, radio and phonograph reproduction; applied for over 800 patents in U.S. and Europe.
Scope and Contents
Printed patents, reports and related material on his system for the radio control of torpedoes, inventions for musical instruments and scrapbooks of newspaper clippings and congressional publications about Hammond and his work. Half the collection is made up of clippings.
Electronic musical instruments; Engineering; Torpedoes; World War, 1914-1918; Albums (Books); Inventors; Hammond, John Hays, 1888-1965
- Inventory
  - "List of inventions of John Hays Hammond, Jr.", undated (Box 1)
  - Index to printed patents, undated (Box 1)
  - Printed patents, 1914-1925 (Box 1)
  - Printed patents, 1921-1935 (Box 2)
  - Printed Patents, 1929-1938 (Box 3)
  - Printed Patents, 1938-1961 (Box 4)
  - List of cases pending, 1962 (Box 4)
  - System for Radio Control of Torpedoes
    - "Proceedings of an informal conference before the Board of Ordnance and Fortification, War Department, on the Subject of the Hammond Radiodynamic system for the control of torpedoes", 1916 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Manual for war game at the Naval War College, Newport, R.I., 1920 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      General
      See also: Box 19
    - "Report on Radiodynamic Control of the U.S.S. Iowa", 1920 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - "Hammond System for Torpedo Fire Control" (3 copies of Vol. I), 1933 (Box 6)
    - "Hammond System for Torpedo Fir Control" (1 copy of Vol. I), 1933 (Box 7)
    - Report, "Hammond Radiodynamic Torpedo Control System," for the U.S. Army Board of Ordnance and Fortification (2 vols.), undated (Box 7)
  - Inventions related to music
    - Concert brochures, 1925-1926 (Box 8)
    - Brochure announcing Hammond's association with the Aeolian Company, undated (Box 8)
    - America and Europe Commend an American Pianist and an American Invention, undated (Box 8)
    - "Expressions from Distinguished Artists on HAMMOND DYNAMIC AMPLIFICATION" (photocopies of letters), 1930 (Box 8)
    - Joseph Bonnet, playing the organ in the John Hays Hammond Museum: Organ Music of the 19th and 20th Centuries, undated (Box 8)
  - "Outline for Telespot Demonstration for Mr. Frank Folson" of wartime applications of television, 1952 (Box 9)
  - Hammond Research Laboratory: New Television Techniques in War: Report Submitted to ... Radio Corporation of America, undated (Box 9)
  - The Franklin Institute of the State of Pennsylvania for the Promotion of Mechanic Arts: report re: awarding Hammond a medal for his work on remote and automatic controls, 1959 (Box 9)
  - Edward H. Lofton: "The History of the Intermediate Frequency," prepared to support Hammond's defense against B. J. Meissner's charge of infringement" (transcript of 1938 report), 1964 (Box 9)
  - Congressional publications referring to Hammond or his work
    - 1920 (Box 10)
    - 1924-1933 (Box 11)
    - 1933-1959 (Box 12)
  - Magazine and newspaper articles and clippings about Hammond or by him
    - 1912-1936 (Box 13)
    - 1941-1947 (Box 14)
    - 1949-1954 (Box 15)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 16)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 17)
    - "John Hays Hammond, Jr.: The Great Inventor Who Lives in a Castle," Worcester Sunday Telegram, Feature Parade, 1960 August 7 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Printed speech by David Sarnoff, 1953 (Box 18)
  - RCA brochures, 1949 (Box 18)
  - Oversize, 1920, 1960 (Box 19)